Lillian B. Gilkes Papers
Lillian B. Gilkes Papers
1900-1976
Gilkes, Lillian B. (Lillian Barnard), 1902-1977.
3 linear ft.
The Lillian B. Gilkes Papers comprises the correspondence, writings, research notes, and memorabilia of the American author, educator, and biographer of Cora Crane (b. 1902). The collection not only illuminates Gilkes' professional writings, but also reveals a personal life marked by political activity and connections with radical artists and writers of the early to mid-20th century.
149513
Biographical History
American author, educator, biographer of Cora Crane.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Lillian B. Gilkes Papers comprises the correspondence, writings, research notes, and memorabilia of the American author, educator, and biographer of Cora Crane (b. 1902). The collection not only illuminates Gilkes' professional writings, but also reveals a personal life marked by political activity and connections with radical artists and writers of the early to mid-20th century.
Spanning the years 1900 to 1976, the alphabetically arranged Correspondence-Subject Files (Boxes 1-4) consists of any combination of incoming and/or outgoing correspondence, clippings, photographs, miscellaneous printed material, and writings. Correspondence includes that of family members (Louise Davidson, Fannie Gilkes, Fannie E. Taylor); authors (Benjamin Appel, Margaret Culkin Banning, Paul Corey, Martha Dodd (Stern), Janet Flanner, Gladys Benjamin Goddard, Josephine Herbst, Robert Hillyer, Langston Hughes, Helen R. Hull, Ruth Lechlitner, Robert Morss Lovett, Grace Lumpkin, Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings, Jennings Rice, Felizia Seyd, Genevieve Taggard, Richard Wright, Leane Zugsmith); Gilkes' co-authors (Millen Brand, Dorothy Brewster); performing artists (Geradine Farrar, Georgette Leblanc, Eva Le Gallienne, Enrico and Dorothy Caruso); political figures (Henry Wallace); and publishers (Margaret C. Anderson, Houghton, Mifflin and Company, and Charles Scribners's Sons). Subject files contain a variety of documents relating to anti-ballistic missile systems, an anti-fascist anthology project, Gilkes' New York University short story writing class, Nixon and Watergate, the Progressive Party (of which Gilkes was a member), and the Southern Tenant Farmers Union and Works Progress Administration (WPA).
Produced between 1926 and 1972, the twenty-two articles, several book reviews, three books, and notes constitute Writings (Boxes 5-6).
Memorabilia (Box 6) includes photographs of Gilkes; printed material, such as clippings, periodicals, British political pamphlets and flyers, Democratic Party publications, and programs; writings by others; and miscellany, including a World War I armband, a "Normandie" hatband, and a photograph.
Related Material
The Lillian Gilkes Research Files on the American realist author Stephen Crane and his wife, Cora, are inventoried and housed in the Stephen Crane Collection.
Subject and Genre Headings
Women Authors; Biography; Radicalism; Alpert, Hollis, 1916-2007.; Anderson, Margaret C.; Appel, Benjamin, 1907-1977.; Babcock, Edwina Stanton.; Banning, Margaret Culkin, 1891-1982.; Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985.; Bigelow, Gordon E.; Brand, Millen, 1906-1980.; Brewster, Dorothy, 1883-1979.; Brickell, Herschel, 1889-1952.; Bruccoli, Matthew J. (Matthew Joseph), 1931-2008.; Caruso, Dorothy.; Caruso, Enrico, 1873-1921.; Corey, Paul.; Davidson, Louise.; Deiss, Joseph Jay.; Dodd, Martha, 1908-1990.; Downes, Anne Miller.; Dykeman, Wilma.; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967.; Fielding, Alfred.; Flanner, Janet, 1892-1978.; Gilkes, Fannie.; Gilkes, Lillian B. (Lillian Barnard), 1902-1977.; Goddard, Gladys Benjamin.; Hard, Margaret M.; Hard, Walter R., 1882-; Herbst, Josephine, 1892-1969.; Hills, Mathilda M.; Hillyer, Robert, 1895-1961.; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967.; Hull, Helen R. (Helen Rose), 1888-1971.; Leblanc, Georgette, 1869-1941.; Lechlitner, Ruth, 1901-1989.; Le Gallienne, Eva, 1899-1991.; Lovett, Robert Morss, 1870-1956.; Lumpkin, Grace.; McBride, Mary Margaret, 1899-1976.; Namara, Marguerite, 1888-; O'Brien, Edward J. (Edward Joseph), 1890-1941.; Rawlings, Marjorie Kinnan, 1896-1953.; Rice, Jennings, 1900-; Schlauch, Margaret, 1898-1986.; Seyd, Felizia.; Taggard, Genevieve, 1894-1948.; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965.; Whipple, Chandler.; Wright, Richard, 1908-1960.; Zugsmith, Leane, 1903-1969.; Charles Scribner's Sons.; Houghton, Mifflin and Company.; Progressive Party (U.S.: 1948); American literature -- 20th century.; Anti-fascist movements -- United States.; Authors, American.; Authors and publishers.; Biographers -- United States.; Europe -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Peace movements -- United States.; Political letter-writing -- United States.; Political oratory -- United States.; Progressivism (United States politics); Soviet Union -- Description and travel.; Soviet Union -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Teachers as authors -- United States.; United States -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; United States -- Exiles.; Women authors, American.; World politics -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Notes (documents); Photographs.; Authors.; Biographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - A, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Alpert, Hollis, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Margaret C., 1948-1970; undated (Box 1)
  - Anti-ballistic missile system letters (Gilkes/U.S. senators) (Box 1)
  - Anti-fascist anthology project, Correspondence - 1937-1938 Writings (Box 1)
  - Appel, Benjamin, 1939-1965; undated (Box 1)
    See also Anti-fascist anthology project
  - Authors League of America, the Authors Guild, 1951 (Box 1)
  - B, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Babcock, Edwina Stanton, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Banning, Margaret Culkin, 1966-1971; undated (Box 1)
  - Bessie, Alvah, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Bigelow, Gordon E., 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Brand, Millen, 1949-1954 (Box 1)
  - Brewer & Warren Inc., 1930 (Box 1)
  - Brewster, Dorothy, 1923-1968; undated; Correspondence (2 folders); Writings - "The Russian Soul: an English Literary Pattern" - The American Scholar, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Brickell, Herschel, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Bruccoli, Matthew, 1974 (Box 1)
    See also Lumpkin, Grace
  - C, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Caruso, Enrico and Dorothy, See Goddard, Gladys Benjamin
  - Corey, Paul, See Anti-fascist anthology project
  - Corey, Paul and Lechlitner, Ruth (Box 1)
  - Costain, Thomas B., See Goddard, Gladys Benjamin
  - D, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Davidson, Louise
    - Correspondence, photographs, 1912-1974; undated (Box 1)
    - American Friends of France, Inc and Morgan, Anne, 1949-1954; correspondence, clippings (Box 1)
    - Farrar, Geraldine, 1946-1967; undated (Box 1)
      See also Taylor, Fannie E.
    - Goddard, Gladys B., 1961-1972 (Box 2)
    - Leblanc, Georgette, 1916-1923; photographs (Box 2)
    - Le Gallienne, Eva, 1953-1956; undated; correspondence, clippings, photographs (Box 2)
    - Writings - "The Alley" - The New Yorker, 11 Jan 1936 (Box 2)
  - Deiss, Joseph Jay, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Dodd, Martha (Stern), 1950-1957; undated; correspondence, clippings (Box 2)
  - Downes, Anne Miller, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Dykeman, Wilma, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Farrar, Geraldine (Box 2)
    Correspondence (1945-1966, undated); Memorabilia, clippings, photographs, printed (1902-1974)
    See also Davidson, Louise
  - Fielding, Alfred, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Flanner, Janet, 1936 (Box 2)
  - G, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Gilkes, Fannie (Lillian Gilkes' mother), 1929-1946; undated; photographs (Box 2)
  - Goddard, Gladys Benjamin
    - Benjamin family, original and copy photographs, and tintypes (2) (Box 2)
    - Caruso, Enrico and Dorothy (Goddard's sister), 1918-1938; Correspondence (copies), clippings, photographs (mostly copies) (Box 2)
    - Goddard, Torrance [pseud.] / Costain, Thomas B., 1927-1962; legal and production records for Wings of Song (Box 2)
    - Johnson, Burgess, 1900 (Box 2)
    - Pryor, Roger A., 1912 (Box 2)
    - Zirato, Bruno and Nina, 1967-1974; correspondence, clippings, photographs (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous thank-you letters, 1928-1976 (Box 3)
    - Writings, ms. of unpublished short story, poems (1908), notes, a drawing (Box 3)
    - Memorabilia (Box 3)
    - Clippings, ms. of obituary by L. Gilkes (Box 3)
  - H, 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Hard, Walter R. and Margaret, 1952-1971 (Box 3)
  - Hemingway, Ernest, 1950; Gilkes' criticisms to editors about reviews of his book, Across the River and Into the Trees - clippings (Box 3)
  - Herbst, Josephine, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
  - Hillyer, Robert, 1949-1953 (Box 3)
  - Hills, Mathilda, See Mayfield, John
  - Houghton, Mifflin and Company, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Hull, Helen R., 1930-1948 (Box 3)
  - J, 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Johnson, Burgess, See Goddard, Gladys Benjamin
  - Korea, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - L, 1 folder (Box 3)
  - League of American Writers (publications), 1938-1941 (Box 3)
  - Leblanc, Georgette, See Davidson, Louise
  - Lechlitner, Ruth and Corey, Paul, 1937-1966 (Box 3)
  - Le Gallienne, Eva, See Davidson, Louise
  - Levesque, Jacques-Henry and Angele, 1972; writings, photographs (Box 3)
  - Lovett, Robert Morss, 1949-1955; undated (Box 3)
  - Lumpkin, Grace, 1930s-1976; undated (Box 3)
  - M, 1 folder (Box 3)
  - McBride, Mary Margaret, 1948-1957 (Box 3)
  - Mayfield, John, 1966-1973; 1977; includes Hills, Mathilda (Box 3)
  - Morgan, Anne, See Davidson, Louise
  - N, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Namara, Marguerite, undated (Box 4)
  - Neruda, Pablo, undated (Box 4)
  - New Masses, 1937-1938 (Box 4)
  - New York University Short Story Writing class, miscellaneous correspondence with the institution and Gilkes' students (Box 4)
  - Richard Nixon Impeachment/Watergate, 1952-1975; correspondence, clippings (Box 4)
  - O, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - O'Brien, Edward J., 1933 (Box 4)
  - P, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Political letters, 1968-1976; incoming and outgoing to governors, presidents, senators (Box 4)
  - Progressive Party
    - Wallace, Henry A. and Ilo, 1938-1975 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1948-1975 (Box 4)
    - Radio and meeting talks by L. Gilkes, typescript ms. and holograph notes (Box 4)
    - Memorabilia, 1948; founding convention pamphlets, programs, delegate pins and IDs (Box 4)
  - Pryor, Roger A., See Goddard, Gladys Benjamin
  - R, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Rawlings, Marjorie Kinnan and Baskin, Norton, 1949-1954 (Box 4)
  - Rice, Jennings, 1935-1949 (Box 4)
  - S, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Schlauch, Margaret, 1947-1972; undated; clippings (Box 4)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1930-1936; clippings (Box 4)
  - Seyd, Felizia, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Solano, Solita, 1962; undated; photograph, writings (Box 4)
  - Southern Tenant Farmers Union and Works Progress Administration (WPA), 1937-1947; photograph, printed material (Box 4)
  - Stern, Martha Dodd, See Dodd, Martha (Stern) (Box 4)
  - T, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Taggard, Genevieve, undated (Box 4)
  - Taylor, Fannie E.
    - Davidson, Louise, 1915-1917; undated; correspondence, clippings, photographs, programs (Box 4)
    - Varesi, Gilda, 1913; correspondence, clippings, photographs, programs (Box 4)
  - United States Works Progress Administration (WPA), See Southern Tenant Farmers Union and Works Progress Administration (WPA)
  - Varesi, Gilda, See Taylor, Fannie E.
  - W, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Wallace, Henry, See photographs in Progressive Party West Side Committee to Aid China
  - Whipple, Chandler, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Wolfson, Norman, 1946; "Hollow Skin" typescript ms. (Box 4)
  - Wright, Richard, 1937-1945 (Box 4)
  - Zirato, Bruno, 1972 (Box 5)
    See also Goddard, Gladys Benjamin
  - Zugsmith, Leane, 1938; correspondence, writings (Box 5)
- Writings (by Gilke)
  - Articles
    - "Afterword for The Wedding, a Novel by Grace Lumpkin", typescript ms. (Box 5)
    - "The Apostate: a Story", Scribner's, Jan 1933 (Box 5)
    - "Barnard Property Acquired by the Barnett First National Bank: Some Jacksonville History", typescript mss. (1 partial) (Box 5)
    - "Experiment at Highlander", Direction, Nov 1939 (Box 5)
    - "Experiment at Highlander", Writers Teach Writing [1940/1941] "Foreword", for the League of American Writers Writers School Bulletin, Spring 1940 - corrected typescript ms., printed material (Box 5)
    - "Further Discussion of the Angene and Botkin Papers", The English Journal, Part II, Feb. 1940 (Box 5)
    - "Get Together! A True Story About the CIO Agricultural Workers Union", The CIO News, July 10, 1939 (Box 5)
    - "Goldilocks and the Red-Herring: a Tale of the Campaign", typescript ms. (Box 5)
    - "Hawthorne, Park Benjamin, and S.G. Goodrich: a Three-Cornered Imbroglio", 1970 (Box 5)
    - "Hope for the South", The Fight, Jan. 1938 (Box 5)
    - "Letter Back Home", New Advance, Oct. 1939 (Box 5)
    - "Life in the Big Cities", n.d.; The Bookman (Box 5)
    - "A New Voice in the Old South", New York Citizen, July 1, 1940 (Box 5)
    - "Oil for Defense", typescript ms. (Box 5)
    - "Owen Whitfield", Equality, Oct./Nov. 1940 (Box 5)
    - "Park Benjamin, Henry William Herbert, and William Gilmore Simms: Some New Light on Old Differences", typescript drafts (Box 5)
    - "Park Benjamin: Literary Agent, Et Cetera", typescript mss. (Box 5)
    - "Taxation and Inflation", 1943 (Box 5)
    - "To the Editor (The Ridgefield Press, 1943): the poll-tax congressman.. .", typescript ms. (Box 5)
    - "The Trial of Preacher Blackstone", Direction, Summer 1942 (Box 5)
    - "Writer Defends Her Parley Piece, Stays Unscalped", The Ridgefield Press, Apr. 20, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Book reviews
    - "Humorous Philosophizing, a Review by Lillian Gilkes", The Book Review, Oct. 1926 (Box 6)
    - "A Study of Selfishness", New York Tribune, Mar. 2, 1924 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous reviews by L. Gilkes, 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Books
    - A Home Study Course in the Technique of the Short Story, 1928; (uncredited author L. Gilkes) prepared under the supervision of the Department of English, Columbia University (Box 6)
    - How to Write for Pleasure and Profit, legal material (Box 6)
    - Short Story Craft, production records - preparatory and legal correspondence with co-author Warren Bower, contributing authors, publisher - miscellaneous letters about book, advertisements, clippings; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Memorabilia (Box 6)
  - Notes, 1 folder (Box 6)
- Photographs
  - Lillian Gilkes, portrait and ID card (Box 6)
- Printed material
  - Clippings
    - Lillian Gilkes related, 1947-1974 (Box 6)
    - Political, 1970-1976; undated (Box 6)
    - War poster by L. Gilkes (clipping), 1917 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940-1972; undated (Box 6)
  - Periodicals
    - Miscellaneous, 1923-1955 (Box 6)
  - Miscellany
    - British political pamphlets and flyers, 1975; from Nicolas Pease (family knew Stephen Crane) (Box 6)
    - Political publications, 1942-1946; Democratic-Independent Club of Ridgefield, Connecticut publications (1943-1945); Democratic Party flyers (1942-1946) (Box 6)
    - Programs, 1927-1934 (Box 6)
- Writings (by others)
  See also Correspondence-subject files: Anti-fascist anthology project
  - Albee, George (Box 6)
  - Appel, Benjamin (Box 6)
  - Arguedas, Jose Maria (Box 6)
  - Brand, Millen (Box 6)
  - Corey, Paul (Box 6)
  - Dorais, Leon (Box 6)
  - Field, Ben (Box 6)
  - Gelhorn, Martha (Box 6)
  - Hellman, Lillian (Box 6)
  - Maltz, Albert (Box 6)
  - Nexo, Martin (Box 6)
  - Pereda, Prudencio de (Box 6)
  - Seyd, Felizia (Box 6)
  - Shinaki, Kensaku (Box 6)
  - Warner, Sylvia W. (Box 6)
  - Wolfe, Thomas (Box 6)
  - Wolfson, Norman, See Correspondence-Subject Files: Wolfson, Norman
  - Zugsmith, Leane, See Correspondence-Subject Files: Zugsmith, Leane
- Miscellany
  - Armband - World War I (Box 6)
  - Hatband - "Normandie" (Box 6)
  - Photograph of Innesley Dorrian (Box 6)